<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Frozen dirt diaries</title><link href="https://egodin.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://egodin.github.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://egodin.github.io/</id><updated>2016-10-29T13:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>CanMars 2016 — this is gonna roll Monday Morning</title><link href="https://egodin.github.io/canmars-2016-this-is-gonna-roll-monday-morning.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-29T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-29T13:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Etienne Godin</name></author><id>tag:egodin.github.io,2016-10-29:/canmars-2016-this-is-gonna-roll-monday-morning.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;For #CANMARS 2016, we are a team where each member has a role. Also, things are moving very fast, and a few last-minute adjustments were required just before the start.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is gonna be awesome. We have been preparing for this event for the last few months. Several participants are veterans of the 2015 mission, leads were there during the first few years of the project. In addition to a handful of new participants such as myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="my-role"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My role.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, there were a few last-minute adjustments in the hierarchical structure of the mission staff at Mission Control. Initially, I was going to be a member of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the GIS group (Geographical Information System), those responsible for organizing maps and geolocalisation features for the rest of the teams, with &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/Zach4TheFuture"&gt;&amp;#64;Zach4TheFuture&lt;/a&gt; (Zach Morse, Western, Ph.D. student in Earth Sciences) and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/Elusieum"&gt;&amp;#64;Elusium&lt;/a&gt; (Elise Harrington, Western, M. Sc. student in Earth Sciences);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the MastCAM group (camera mounted on a mast, with a ZOOM and PANORAMA mode);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the TEMMI group (the Three-Dimensional Exploration Multispectral Microscope Imager) with a colleague.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big load as they say. I have been reading for the last weeks almost everything that was written on those sensors so I have a good grasp on capabilities and limitations, in addition to reports and papers that were prepared for conferences and such.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good for me! Next thing I know, as the team was taking form and specific schedules and limitations of availability were arriving on the Science Lead desk, a few adjustments were required:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple" start="4"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was removed from the GIS team;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I became the lead for the MastCAM group;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the lead of TEMMI;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the lead of RMI (the Remote Micro Imager);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the lead of WATSON (a special camera acting as a microscope).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was not sure yet who would be composing my group but I had a few remote collaborators online who would help me run this fine suite of instruments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still have the weekend to somewhat catch on with my latest assignment(s).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="MESR, the Mars Exploration Science Rover" src="https://egodin.github.io/images/MESR.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Source: ASC_CSA. This is MESR being tested in a simulated arid environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="UWO CanMars"></category></entry><entry><title>The best taxi on this planet</title><link href="https://egodin.github.io/the-best-taxi-on-this-planet.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-18T19:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-07-18T19:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Etienne Godin</name></author><id>tag:egodin.github.io,2016-07-18:/the-best-taxi-on-this-planet.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;A rainy evening. Everyone eager to get at destination.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Everyone is near the tarmac, in full expedition gear, ready to leave to Devon. Light rain, sky is gray, it is frisky as usual. We just got a &lt;strong&gt;GO&lt;/strong&gt; from the PCSP control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We spent the last two days making and weighing boxes, as everything getting in the taxi need to be known up to the nearest 10 kg by the pilot - when we were allowed a bit less than 1.5 tons, passengers included. So what is this taxi about? Well, in my opinion, this is the best ride you will ever have in a taxi, trust me. To have an idea, check Fig. 1. I mean, seriously - this is like a combo = the pilots are awesome, they can land litterally anywhere, which is a good thing because when in High Latitudes, it is not like there is a landstrip every two miles right. Control makes sure that the weather is perfect, which may be challenging sometime. I have been flying these almost yearly since 2009 - landing on frozen lakes mostly, and with climate changes, frozen lakes are not to be trusted based on the date right, so one need to be careful. Anyway we are now going in a polar desert this time, so the risk of finding a frozen lake in July is low.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Twin Otter" src="https://egodin.github.io/images/Twin.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Figure 1&lt;/em&gt;: Twin Otter are awesome planes able to land and takeoff literally anywhere. Here is the two Twin full of our gear waiting for the GO from control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These planes are Twin Otter, owned and operated by Kenn Borek. There was three Twin Otter in rotation at Resolute this summer, and we were schedule 2 (to make 3 trips) to destination on Devon. I was assigned to the third and last one. These Twin are doing service to the Antarctic apparently, during northern hemisphere winter. Usually, more work is done during summer in high latitudes, depending on the project. In our case when the snow cover the ground, it is very unpractical to work, especially during the long nights where not much can be seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These planes are essential to research in remote area, since they can bring a lot of supply to extended stays, which is the case this summer with almost one month for about half the group, some are leaving after two weeks and other should replace them. See Figure 2 to have an idea of what is entering in one single plane, not counting ATV's and personal - we had 3 loads like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Twin Otter" src="https://egodin.github.io/images/Stuff.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Figure 2&lt;/em&gt;: This is what is entering in one Twin Otter, not counting the team or the extra ATV's. We had 3 like that, one for each plane. Mostly scientific equipment, gear and supplies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="UWO"></category><category term="Twin Otter"></category><category term="Taxi"></category></entry><entry><title>Arrival at Resolute, NU</title><link href="https://egodin.github.io/arrival-at-resolute-nu.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-16T09:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-07-16T09:30:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Etienne Godin</name></author><id>tag:egodin.github.io,2016-07-16:/arrival-at-resolute-nu.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;Resolute Bay - my first time ever on Cornwallis Island; and I will finally meet the PCSP staff in person, after all these years over the long-wave radio and Iridium!&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Just arrived at Resolute Bay, Nunavut, yesterday. This is presently my first time on Cornwallis Island and also the most northern location I ever went.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="PCSP" src="https://egodin.github.io/images/PCSP072016.JPG" style="width: 300px;" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Polar Continental Shelf Program Resolute facility is an invaluable resource for researchers working in the High Arctic (15 July 2016).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact this place is amazing, seriously, in regard with the logistics provided and their support for our research. Staff from PSCP (Salut Yvon!) were waiting for my arrival with a pick-up truck to help me with my with my gear. The airstrip is conveniently connecting to the Storage and very near the main building so the transition between 'being seated in the aircraft' to 'let's show you your room and the kitchen' was a 10 minutes thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon arrival I was the only one from my team, the rest of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.spacerocks.ca/"&gt;Spacerocks&lt;/a&gt; et al. were still transiting to destination. No worry I was busy; since we will be on Devon Island for up to three weeks, with 10 to 13 persons at once, I had to start looking at the state of the field gear that was left in Gordon's shelf, in addition to what will be provided by PCSP for our stay. So, let's begin by the beginning:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tripod, for optical equipments? Check.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ATV's x4, those Bayou 250? Check.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Honda power generator, one 1000W to carry around during the day? Check.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another power generator (2000W) for the base camp? Check.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tents (Eureka K-2 XT) x9? Check. (more were carried up by the team).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This field portable toilet? Check.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and so on...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there is so much more small and not so small things to check and to prepare and, luckily, the rest of the team will be there very soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="UWO"></category></entry><entry><title>Wilderness and Remote First Aid Training</title><link href="https://egodin.github.io/wilderness-and-remote-first-aid-training.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-05-28T20:55:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-05-28T20:55:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Etienne Godin</name></author><id>tag:egodin.github.io,2016-05-28:/wilderness-and-remote-first-aid-training.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;This training is critical and a prerequisite to travel to places such as Devon Island, where medical intervention, if required, is likely to be extremely limited.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Previous to travelling to the High Arctic, it is usual to be trained in CPR or First Aid of some sort. Nevertheless, our research group required everyone travelling to Devon Island this year to have a valid Wilderness and Remote First Aid Certification. Three of us went to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.lmac-cpr.ca/wildremotefirstaid.html"&gt;LMac Community CPR&lt;/a&gt;. The main difference with the Wilderness and Remote course, compared to other more classical courses, is that we have a very poor access to emergency services, so the time required before an evacuation or the arrival of a health professional can be dozen hours or a few days, depending on the weather and our location. When an emergency occur, care must be provided for much longer, where in any urban area about fifteen minutes will be considered quite long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were 3 from our team at the course, where we practiced the order of action during an intervention (Primary, Secondary checks, etc). There was a strong emphasis on simulated and mocked accidents, often impossible to resolve or with 'deadly' outcomes, where we had to put our mind to work and try to save the folks that were recoverable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trainers were very competent and were also putting a lot of work to make the scenarios as realist as possible. In the picture, the rescuers in training thought that the wounded could have a neck injury and therefore secured it before transporting the victim in a shelter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Mocked wound" src="https://egodin.github.io/images/firstaid.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;This is an example of the situation we had to deal with - without access to 911 of course. Credits LMac-CPR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a great training - always in the hope we do not really need it right...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More pictures from the training here : &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.lmac-cpr.ca/wildgallery.html"&gt;LMac Community CPR : action pics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>Objective : Devon Island</title><link href="https://egodin.github.io/objective-devon-island.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-05-13T16:07:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-05-13T16:07:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Etienne Godin</name></author><id>tag:egodin.github.io,2016-05-13:/objective-devon-island.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;This is it. Devon Island it will be! This will be quite something - as I never had the chance to visit a polar desert before. Most places I went to were quite green and wet (wetlands). Also every place I visited up to now is located south of Devon Island too.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here is a map of the location of our projected fieldwork:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Devon Island" src="https://egodin.github.io/images/devon.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Devon Island is located 74 degrees North. There is an ice cap on the eastern side of the Island, and the impact structure where we will stay is on the western side of the Island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will be about 13 at most in the camp, and a small switch of personal midcourse. We will arrive at Resolute Bay facilities (PCSP) around July 15 and leave the Arctic around August 10. It will be an extraordinary experience to work with new peoples at a new emplacement. Can't wait to be there. Still have to prepare the scientific program, time is running!&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="UWO"></category></entry><entry><title>Arrival at London</title><link href="https://egodin.github.io/arrival-at-london.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-05-02T16:07:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-05-02T16:07:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Etienne Godin</name></author><id>tag:egodin.github.io,2016-05-02:/arrival-at-london.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;I just arrived in London, ON, after leaving early from Montreal using VIARail Train. Actually I could use to fly with WestJet to London, but flying from Montreal is not always convenient, and when given the choice, I either use ground transport, or plainly another airport (Hello YOW and BTV!).&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Middlesex College" src="https://egodin.github.io/images/MiddlesexCollegeUWO.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;This is a view of the Middlesex College on the UWO Campus, just next my office&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here I am in London. It is my second time here, the first time being when I went to meet Dr. Osinski (CPSX &amp;#64; Western) for an hour last Fall, (back and through from Montreal). Now I am to work with him for the next two years due to my project being funded by the FQRNT. This will be awesome! Tomorrow I hope to meet my colleagues, visit our lab, the campus, (the libraries of course). Will further need to settle down, find a room. I got a lot of people to meet. So it is starting quite well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This building next door is named Middlesex College - but most importantly it hosts the Grad Club, a friendly place where there is plenty of coffee, bananas and hot food. I already know that this will be my supply place. The campus is quite green - trees and grass everywhere and the weather feels like the warmest Montreal summer days - must be an effect from the Great Lakes nearby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My assigned office is in the Western Science Centre building - it is a temporary assignment since post-doctoral researchers are grouped together somewhere else, I should be able to settle soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="UWO"></category></entry><entry><title>A new project</title><link href="https://egodin.github.io/a-new-project.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-04-22T15:55:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-04-22T15:55:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Etienne Godin</name></author><id>tag:egodin.github.io,2016-04-22:/a-new-project.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;So I just got a great research scholarship.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is among the greatest day of my life today: I got a post-doctoral research scholarship from FQRNT! They accepted my project to study permafrost features, dynamics and gullies at the Haughton Impact Structure (or crater). The study site is located in the western part of Devon Island, Nunavut, Canadian Arctic Archipelago. The approach consists in studying Earth cold and arid geomorphology in polar regions and use this to enhance our understanding of similar processes and landforms on Mars. I am right away planning my move to London (ON) at Western - this is gonna be amazing!&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry></feed>