<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Frozen dirt diaries - Blog</title><link href="https://egodin.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://egodin.github.io/feeds/blog.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://egodin.github.io/</id><updated>2016-05-28T20:55:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Wilderness and Remote First Aid Training</title><link href="https://egodin.github.io/wilderness-and-remote-first-aid-training.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-05-28T20:55:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-05-28T20:55:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Etienne Godin</name></author><id>tag:egodin.github.io,2016-05-28:/wilderness-and-remote-first-aid-training.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;This training is critical and a prerequisite to travel to places such as Devon Island, where medical intervention, if required, is likely to be extremely limited.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Previous to travelling to the High Arctic, it is usual to be trained in CPR or First Aid of some sort. Nevertheless, our research group required everyone travelling to Devon Island this year to have a valid Wilderness and Remote First Aid Certification. Three of us went to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.lmac-cpr.ca/wildremotefirstaid.html"&gt;LMac Community CPR&lt;/a&gt;. The main difference with the Wilderness and Remote course, compared to other more classical courses, is that we have a very poor access to emergency services, so the time required before an evacuation or the arrival of a health professional can be dozen hours or a few days, depending on the weather and our location. When an emergency occur, care must be provided for much longer, where in any urban area about fifteen minutes will be considered quite long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were 3 from our team at the course, where we practiced the order of action during an intervention (Primary, Secondary checks, etc). There was a strong emphasis on simulated and mocked accidents, often impossible to resolve or with 'deadly' outcomes, where we had to put our mind to work and try to save the folks that were recoverable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trainers were very competent and were also putting a lot of work to make the scenarios as realist as possible. In the picture, the rescuers in training thought that the wounded could have a neck injury and therefore secured it before transporting the victim in a shelter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Mocked wound" src="https://egodin.github.io/images/firstaid.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;This is an example of the situation we had to deal with - without access to 911 of course. Credits LMac-CPR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a great training - always in the hope we do not really need it right...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More pictures from the training here : &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.lmac-cpr.ca/wildgallery.html"&gt;LMac Community CPR : action pics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>Arrival at London</title><link href="https://egodin.github.io/arrival-at-london.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-05-02T16:07:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-05-02T16:07:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Etienne Godin</name></author><id>tag:egodin.github.io,2016-05-02:/arrival-at-london.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;I just arrived in London, ON, after leaving early from Montreal using VIARail Train. Actually I could use to fly with WestJet to London, but flying from Montreal is not always convenient, and when given the choice, I either use ground transport, or plainly another airport (Hello YOW and BTV!).&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Middlesex College" src="https://egodin.github.io/images/MiddlesexCollegeUWO.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;This is a view of the Middlesex College on the UWO Campus, just next my office&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here I am in London. It is my second time here, the first time being when I went to meet Dr. Osinski (CPSX &amp;#64; Western) for an hour last Fall, (back and through from Montreal). Now I am to work with him for the next two years due to my project being funded by the FQRNT. This will be awesome! Tomorrow I hope to meet my colleagues, visit our lab, the campus, (the libraries of course). Will further need to settle down, find a room. I got a lot of people to meet. So it is starting quite well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This building next door is named Middlesex College - but most importantly it hosts the Grad Club, a friendly place where there is plenty of coffee, bananas and hot food. I already know that this will be my supply place. The campus is quite green - trees and grass everywhere and the weather feels like the warmest Montreal summer days - must be an effect from the Great Lakes nearby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My assigned office is in the Western Science Centre building - it is a temporary assignment since post-doctoral researchers are grouped together somewhere else, I should be able to settle soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="UWO"></category></entry><entry><title>A new project</title><link href="https://egodin.github.io/a-new-project.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-04-22T15:55:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-04-22T15:55:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Etienne Godin</name></author><id>tag:egodin.github.io,2016-04-22:/a-new-project.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;So I just got a great research scholarship.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is among the greatest day of my life today: I got a post-doctoral research scholarship from FQRNT! They accepted my project to study permafrost features, dynamics and gullies at the Haughton Impact Structure (or crater). The study site is located in the western part of Devon Island, Nunavut, Canadian Arctic Archipelago. The approach consists in studying Earth cold and arid geomorphology in polar regions and use this to enhance our understanding of similar processes and landforms on Mars. I am right away planning my move to London (ON) at Western - this is gonna be amazing!&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry></feed>